Guide to the Montana Volunteers records 1867-1868
Montana Historical Society
Montana Volunteers Records
1867-1868
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 162
Montana Volunteers.
.2 linear feet of shelf space
The Montana Volunteers was a volunteer military organization, primarily cavalry, formed by Executive directive to combat perceived Indian threats in the Territory. These records (1867-1868) consist of correspondence, financial records, reports, and miscellany, largely for the District of Helena.
The 1st Regiment of Montana Volunteers was formed in July 1867 by executive order of Governor Green Clay Smith. The formation of the regiment was in response to the perceived increased threat of attacks by Sioux and other tribes. The regiment was divided into nine companies under the general command of Col. Thomas Thoroughman. He was directed by the governor to "send out from time to time such forces as may be deemed necessary to chastise marauding and guerilla bands of Indians." Quartermaster and Commissary officers were appointed to secure needed supplies. By August, Neil Howie had taken command of the forces.
These records consist of correspondence, financial records, reports, and miscellany, largely for the District of Helena.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Dakota Indians--Wars, 1865-1868; Military bases--Montana--Supplies and stores; Military service, Voluntary--Montana
Fort Thomas Francis Meagher (Mont.)
Montana; Military; Native Americans
Detailed Description of the Collection
- General Correspondence
  - Chronological (correspondents include Amara Cobb, Governor Green Clay Smith, Captain George M. Pinney, Adjutant General Martin Beem, Captain W. S. Scribner, Captain N. S. Turner, A. M. S. Carpenter, Scott J. Armstrong), 1867 May-November (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - General and Special Orders of Territorial Headquarters of the District of Helena, 1867 July-September (Box-folder 1 / 2)
- Financial Records
  - Requisitions, receipts, and statements, 1867-1868 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
- Legal Documents
  - Contracts and personal bonds, 1867-1868 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
- Reports
  - Reports of Commanding Officer Neil Howie, 1867 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
- Miscellany
  - Muster roll, enlistments, discharges, 1867 (Box-folder 1 / 6)